Guide to the Elsa Guerdrum Allen papers, 1885-1976,
Allen, Elsa Guerdrum papers, 1885-1976
- Series III. Research and Manuscripts by Elsa Allen
  - Loose Notes and Bibliographic Cards
    - Loose Bibliographic Cards, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
      Mainly for John Abbot of Georgia
    - Bibliographic Cards, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Loose Notes, Pages and Bibliographic Cards, undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
      Found with John Abbot Materials
    - Bibliographic Cards and Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Bibliographic Notes and Cards for John Abbot of Georgia and The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon, undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Bibliographic Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - General Ornithology Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Loose Materials, undated (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Loose Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Loose Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 18)
      Includes part of a write up in memorial to Professor Hoyt
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards: The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon, Cornell Library, John Abbot and Misc., undated (Box 23)
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards: General Ornithology, John Abbot and Misc., undated (Box 23)
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards: Bird poetry, History of American Ornithology Before Audubon and misc., undated (Box 23)
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards for "After Audubon" and Early American Bird Poetry, undated (Box 23)
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards: John Abbot Research and some marked "Not for Abbot", undated (Box 24)
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards: Unspecified Research, undated (Box 24)
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards: Unspecified Research, undated (Box 24)
    - Box of Bibliographic Cards: Mainly John Abbot Research, undated (Box 24)
    - Metal Box of Bibliographic Cards: Mainly Alexander Wilson Research, undated (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Bulletins, Announcements and Fellowship Notes, c. 1930s (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Museum and Gallery Brochures, 1949-1953 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - Charges from Libraries and Museums for Charges relating to Ornithological Research, 1957-1959 (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - Science and Travel Bulletins, 1958-1967 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - Library of Congress, Information Bulletin, December 29, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 23)
      Highlighted article regarding the creation of "A National Union Catalog of Manuscript Collections"
    - Ornithology Notes, Correspondence with Bradley Martin and Trial Will (for distribution of her possessions.), 1965 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Kennedy Art Gallery Catalog, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 25)
      "American Drawings, Pastels and Watercolors: Part Two The Nineteenth Century, 1825-1890
    - Various Advertisements and Fliers, dated and undated (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Transcript of a Charles Lamb Sale and handwritten letter, undated (Box 19, Folder 27)
    - 2 Printing Blocks of Birds (possibly for The History of Ornithology Before Audubon), undated (Box 22)
      Note: except for these two Blocks the rest have been distributed. Some have been kept for exhibition purposes (I. Wald)
- Series IV. Articles and Reprints
  - Articles and Reprints by Elsa Allen
    - Nature Study Review and "Winter Birds" Reprint, 1917 and 1923 (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - Clippings of Articles Written by Elsa Allen, 1920 and 1935 (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - Reprints from The Auk, 1936-1950 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    - The Habits and Life History of the Eastern Chipmunk, Tamias Striatus Lysteri by Elsa Allen in the New York State Museum Bulletin, 1938 (Box 20, Folder 27)
    - Birding on the Cornell Plantations - in the Cornell Plantations, 1944-1945 (Box 20, Folder 28)
    - "The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon" in Transactions of the American Philosophical Society, Volume 41, Part 2, 1951 (Box 20)
    - The American Career of Alexander Wilson: Father of American Ornithology from the Atlantic Naturalist, 1952 (Box 20, Folder 29)
    - Reprints from The Auk, 1903-1952 (Box 20, Folder 30)
    - Reprints from Various Journals and Bulletins, 1908-1963 (Box 20, Folder 31)
    - Non-Ornithology Related Publications, 1911-1934 (Box 20, Folder 32)
    - Various Journals and Booklets (not reprints), 1911-1953 (Box 20, Folder 33)
    - Reprints from the Wilson Bulletin, 1943-1961 (Box 20, Folder 34)
  - Articles and Reprints by Others
    - Review of History of The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon, c. 1951 (Box 20, Folder 35)
    - " Dr. Elsa Allen Writes Monumental Book" in To Dragma of Alpha Omicron Pi, Spring, 1952 (Box 20, Folder 36)
    - Reprints from the Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, 1952-1959 (Box 20, Folder 37)
    - The American Philosophical Society Library Bulletin, 1954 (Box 20, Folder 38)
    - Various Journals and Booklets (not reprints), 1957-1965 (Box 20, Folder 39)
    - Cantwell, Robert - Articles and Correspondence, c. 1960-1966 (Box 20, Folder 40)
      "A legend Comes to Life: Mark Catesby", "Grey Owl: Mysterious Genius of Nature Lore" and "High Road to a Wild Paradise"
- Series V. Professional Affiliations
  - Ornithological Organizations
    - American Ornithologists Union Meetings, 1913-1914 (Box 19, Folder 28)
    - American Ornithologists Union, 1924-1967 (Box 19, Folder 29)
      Newsletters, Brochures and Programs
    - American Ornithological Union, 1942-1954 (Box 19, Folder 30)
      Includes manuscripts by Elsa Allen, correspondence, and brochures
    - Ornithology Organizations, 1914-1967 (Box 19, Folder 31)
    - The Charles Lamb Society Bulletin, 1941-1959 (Box 19, Folder 32)
    - The Charles Lamb Society, 1941-1957 (Box 19, Folder 33)
      Includes Correspondence and Annual Reports
    - Alaskan Science Conference, November 9-11, 1950 (Box 19, Folder 34)
    - International Ornithological Society, 1950-1952 (Box 19, Folder 35)
      Correspondence and 1950 Congress Program
  - Women's Issues
    - Women's Equality and the Status of Women Materials, 1930's and 1940's (Box 19, Folder 36)
    - "Women's Place: The New Alliance of 'Science' and Anti-Feminism" by Ethel Goldwater from Commentary Magazine, December, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 37)
    - Announcements and Publications, 1947-1957 (Box 19, Folder 38)
      Publications of the Women's Press, Mandatory Jury Duty Advocated for Women and an announcement for the first "Who's Who of American Women"
    - American Association of University Women Newsletter, 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 39)
    - American Association of University Women, General Director's Letter, 1949-1950 (Box 19, Folder 40)
    - Articles and Organizations, undated (Box 19, Folder 41)
  - Cornell University and the Laboratory of Ornithology
    - Summer School Excursions, c. 1923-1933 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Book lists, field trips and song sheets
    - Cornell University Memorabilia, c. 1928 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Cornell Women's Club of Ithaca, 1935-1936 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Elsa Allen was President in 1936
    - Invitation to New Laboratory of Ornithology Collections in Fernow Hall, November 23, 1936 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - "Bird Lore, Old and New" A Summer School Lecture, July 03, 1944 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Notes on the History of Ornithology at Cornell, c. 1946-1955 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Includes a proposed itinerary for the Cornell-National Geographic Expedition in 1946 and a brief summery of Cornell's gift of Audubon's Birds of America
    - Newsletters, Announcements and Class Schedules, 1951-1966 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - History of Ornithology Exhibit at Cornell University Library, 1952 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      Exhibit Notes
    - Arthur Allen's Itinerary for Fall 1953 and a Biographical Sketch of Elsa Allen, c. 1953 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Cornell History, 1860 and 1954 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Includes a 1860 article about Cornell University in "The Leisure Hour" magazine
    - Guest Lists for Cornell University Events, 1956-1957 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Programs and Invitations for Cornell University Events, 1957-1968 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Labels used for the History of Ornithology Exhibit at Cornell University, 1962 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      Notes that it was at "old" library - Uris?
    - History and Literature of Ornithology Lecture Notes, undated (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Notes for a lecture entitled "The Method of Migration Study at Cornell University", undated (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - "Cornell University Presented with Elephant Folio Edition of Audubon's Birds of America" by Elsa Allen, undated (Box 20, Folder 16)
      Speech?
    - Lists of Books at the Laboratory of Ornithology and the Cornell Library, undated (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - "A Word from the Fuertes Reading Room", 1952 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Laboratory of Ornithology, 1954-1968 (Box 20, Folder 19)
      Lab Newsletters, brochures and Correspondence
    - Arthur Allen and David Allen Screen Tour Itinerary, Spring 1959 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Laboratory of Ornithology - brochures and announcement regarding the Library of Natural Sounds, undated (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Laboratory of Ornithology - Letterhead (including some from the Department of Zoology), undated (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Laboratory of Ornithology - Dedication sign for the Louis Agassiz Fuertes Reading Room, undated (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Zoology Party - Event List, undated (Box 20, Folder 24)
- Series VI. Photographic Materials and Illustrations
  - General
    - Louis Fuertes Bird Illustrations, undated (Box 21, Folder 39)
      Prints from a bird guide
    - Prints of Dog Illustrations illustrated by Louis Agassiz Fuertes, undated (Box 21, Folder 40)
    - Prints and Photographs of Birds, undated (Box 21, Folder 41)
    - Image of a bird and empty slide sleeve, undated (Box 21, Folder 42)
    - Birds of Western Canada Poster and Illustrated Bird Postcards, undated (Box 21, Folder 43)
    - Small painting of a baby Black and Pintail Duck by A. Holhbaum, 1933 (Box 21, Folder 44)
    - New Zealand Birds - Mr. Fay? - Loose Illustrations, undated (Box 21, Folder 45)
      Not Original Prints
    - Bird Anatomy, undated (Box 21, Folder 46)
    - Reproductions of Audubon Prints, undated (Box 21, Folder 47)
    - Chipmunk Study Photographs, undated (Box 21, Folder 48)
      Also includes a photo of Arthur Allen with birds and one of Elsa's daughters
    - Catesby Photographs and Photostats, undated (Box 21, Folder 49)
    - Illustration from "Alexander Wilson: Naturalist and Pioneer" by Robert Cantwell, undated (Box 21, Folder 50)
    - "Grouse from Dave", undated (Box 21)
      Rolled up print of a bird
    - W.W. Ellis, undated (Box 21, Folder 51)
      Negatives: Possibly for the History of Ornithology Exhibit at Cornell
    - Cornell Exhibit Materials, undated (Box 21, Folder 52)
      Photographs of early ornithologists and labels used for the exhibition.
    - History of Ornithology Exhibit at Olin Library at Cornell University, 1962 (Box 21, Folder 53)
      35mm Slides
    - Paul Wilhelm, Duke of Wurttemberg, undated (Box 21, Folder 54)
    - History of Ornithology, undated (Box 21, Folder 55)
      Negatives and prints
    - European Ornithologists, undated (Box 22)
      These are 35mm slides with glass casings still in their Kodak boxes
    - Ornithological Illustrations, undated (Box 22)
    - Box of Black and White Negatives of Bird Illustrations (unlabeled) and Bird Skeleton Illustrations by Volcher Coiter, undated (Box 22)
    - Mark Catesby photostats, undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Birds of Western Canada Poster, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Maps, undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Peale Study: Photographs of Ornithological Illustrations, undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Chipmunk Study Photographs and an Illustration, undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Photograph of a Grouse taken by David Allen, undated (Box 26)
      In a small tube
    - "Penguino Dell'America Settentrionale" Print by Guiseppe Maria Terreni, 1763 (Folder 1)
      Illustration from "Il Gazzettiere Americano - Volume Trezo"
    - Illustrations from "A Natural History of Birds" by Eleazar Albin and Elizabeth Albin, c. 1731-1738 (Folder 1)
      Three prints: Macao #11 (colored by Elizabeth), The Brant Goose #93 and The Sheldrake of Bergander #94
    - "Le Magnifique" by Viellot, undated (Folder 1)
      Uncolored Print
    - "Baltimore Oriole and a Tulip Tree" by Mark Catesby, undated (Folder 1)
      Color Reproduction
    - "Pterygophorus, cinctus" Entomology Illustration, undated (Folder 1)
      Two names appear on the illustration: Leach and W. Goodall
    - Hand Drawn Illustrations of Squirrels and Birds, undated (Folder 1)
      Possibly by Louis Agassiz Fuertes
    - 2 pages of test prints of birds by Louis Agassiz Fuertes, undated (Folder 1)
    - Duck Hawk Illustration, undated (Folder 1)
  - The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon
    - Early Ornithologists and Ornithological Prints, undated (Box 21, Folder 56)
      Negatives and Prints
    - Photographs of Illustrations of Ornithologists, undated (Box 21, Folder 57)
      John Ray, Pierre Belon, Sir Hans Sloane and Francis Willoughby
    - Ornithologists, undated (Box 21, Folder 58)
      Negatives
    - Samuel Hearne's name chiseled by himself into the hard rock surface at Sloop's Cove, Manitoba, Canada, undated (Box 21, Folder 59)
      Prints
    - W.W. Ellis Photographs of Drawings, 1955 (Box 21, Folder 60)
    - List of the photographic materials used in preparation for the book, undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
      oversize
    - Photographs of Bird Drawings and Ornithologist Portraits, undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Photograph copy of Samuel Purchase, undated (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Louis Jean Pierre Vieillot - Photostats, undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - George Edwards - Photostats of illustrations, undated (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Photostats of illustrations used in American Ornithology Before Audubon, undated (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Illustrations for Nashville Lecture, undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Box of Glass Negatives of Ornithological Prints, undated (Box 26)
      Also contains a photo of Elsa Allen
  - John Abbot of Georgia
    - John Abbot's Red-headed Woodpecker for The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon, undated (Box 21, Folder 61)
      Print
    - Illustrations for Abbot Book, undated (Box 21, Folder 62)
      Prints and Negatives, also includes some illustrations for The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon
    - John Abbot - Photographs for book, undated (Box 21, Folder 63)
    - Photographs and Copies of John Abbot Materials, undated (Box 21, Folder 64)
      Black and White Prints and Negatives of Illustrations, the John Abbot Memorial, William Swainson Warbler and La Frenaye's Album of Labels
    - Insect Drawing for Chapter XI and Negative of Abbot Spider Drawing, undated (Box 21, Folder 65)
      Prints and Negatives
    - Abbot Negatives and Print, undated (Box 21, Folder 66)
    - John Abbot Memorial Dedication, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of Historical Locations and Markers in Georgia and of an Abbot drawing of "Stuartia" (Stewartia) Flower, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - John Abbot Drawings Returned by Robert Cantwell, undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Abbot's Firsts (1), undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Abbot's Firsts (2), undated (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Abbot's Firsts, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - John Abbot Materials and Jean Alphonse Boisduval, undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Rolls 1-5 - Manchester, undated (Box 22)
      35mm Negatives
    - Roll 6 - Tring 1-35, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 7 - Tring 36-71, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 8 - Tring 72-106, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 9 - Tring 107-116 - Bloomsbury 139-116, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 10 - Bloomsbury: Volume 1, 1-5, Title Page and Handwriting; Volume 2, 140-166, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 11 - Bloomsbury: Volume 1, 6-44, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 12 - Bloomsbury: Volume 1, 43-79, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 13 - Bloomsbury: Volume 1, 79-114, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 14 - Bloomsbury: Volume 2, 166-195, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 15 - Bloomsbury: Volume 2, 195-228, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 16 - Bloomsbury: Volume 2, 229-268, undated (Box 22)
    - Roll 17 - Bloomsbury: Last Ones, undated (Box 22)
    - Photostats of John Abbot Letters, undated (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Photostats Re: Abbots Role in the Revolutionary War and a Map of Georgia Parishes and Counties, undated (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Illustrations for John Abbot Book (1), undated (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Illustrations for John Abbot Book (2), undated (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Photostats of Insects of Georgia by John Abbot, undated (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Oversized photostats, undated (Folder 2)
    - 35mm Slides
      - Abbot Insects at the Carnegie Museum - #1-100, 1952-1953 (Box 22, Folder 8)
        Includes extras
      - Abbot Insects at the Carnegie Museum, undated (Box 22, Folder 9)
        For Book Chapter?
      - Abbot Insects at Emory University - #1-72, undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
        Not complete
      - Abbot Insects at Emory University, undated (Box 22, Folder 11)
        Not numbered against originals
      - Abbot Insects at Emory University - #59-72, undated (Box 22, Folder 12)
        Many to be retaken
      - Abbot Insects at Emory University - To be Retaken, undated (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - Abbot Butterfly and Orllioptera at Emory University, undated (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - Abbot Birds - Summer and Scarlet Tanager, undated (Box 22, Folder 15)
      - Abbot Birds - Warblers, Orioles, and Bobolink, undated (Box 22, Folder 16)
      - Abbot Birds - Wood duck, undated (Box 22, Folder 17)
        Privately Owned
      - Abbot Set of Birds and Flowers - Mr. W.C. Brown, Jr., Benton, SC, undated (Box 22, Folder 18)
      - Abbot Birds - Emma Hartridge, Hopkins College, undated (Box 22, Folder 19)
      - Abbot Birds - Knowsley Hall, Cambridge, Natural History Museum, Georgia, British Museum and Manchester Chetham's Library, undated (Box 22, Folder 20)
        Note inside one of the slide boxes reads" Abbot's Firsts, not complete - used at Seminar talk November 12, 1962
      - Abbot Birds and Insects, undated (Box 22, Folder 21)
        From Metal Slide Box marked "Abbot" - mostly bindings, title pages and a few illustrations
      - Abbot Related, undated (Box 22, Folder 22)
        Bindings, Title pages, illustration and Goodhall House
      - Abbot - To be copied, undated (Box 22, Folder 23)
        Birds, Insects, Title Page and Specimen
      - Abbot Birds - Tests, undated (Box 22, Folder 24)
      - Abbot Birds - Slides for the Wilson Club Talk, undated (Box 22, Folder 25)
        Also includes and image of Arthur Allen
      - Birds Confused with Abbot's Lesser Black Woodpecker, undated (Box 22, Folder 26)
        Specimens
      - Specimens and William Swainson Drawings, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 27)
      - Photographs of England and Images of Bird Specimens, undated (Box 22, Folder 28)
      - Knowsley Hall - Discards, c. 1953 (Box 22, Folder 29)
        John Abbot?
      - William Bartram - Knowsley Hall, c. 1953 (Box 22, Folder 30)
      - William Bartram, George Edwards and Unlabeled - Knowsley Hall, c. 1953 (Box 22, Folder 31)
      - John Eatton LeConte - Turtles and Batrachian at the University of Georgia, undated (Box 22, Folder 32)
      - Bird Illustrations and Extra Slide Labels, undated (Box 22, Folder 33)
        Illustrations are unmarked (not Abbot? - Bartram?)
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 1, undated (Box 22, Folder 34)
        Loons, Grebes, Pelicans, Cormorant, Herons, Ibis, Anatidae
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 2, undated (Box 22, Folder 35)
        Teals, Shovellers, Ducks, Canvasbacks, Lesser Seaups, Goldeneyes, Buffleheads, Mergansers, Vultures, Kites, Hawks
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 3, undated (Box 22, Folder 36)
        Hawks, Eagles, Ospreys, Falcons, Bobwhites, Whooping Cranes, Limpkins, Rails, Soras, Coots, Gallinules, Oyster Catchers, Plovers, Killdeers, Woodcocks, Snipes, Curlews
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 4, undated (Box 22, Folder 37)
        Godwits, Gulls, Sandpipers, Yellowlegs, Terns, Willets, Doves, Pigeons, Plovers
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 5, undated (Box 22, Folder 38)
        Cuckoos, Owls, Whip-poor Wills, Night Hawks, Chimney Swifts, Hummingbirds, Kingfishers, Woodpeckers, Sapsuckers, Flickers
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 6, undated (Box 22, Folder 39)
        Woodpeckers, Kingbirds, Flycatchers, Phoebes, Pewees, Larks, Swallows, Martins, Blue Jays, Crows, Chickadees, Titmouse, Nuthatches, Brown Creepers,
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 7, undated (Box 22, Folder 40)
        Waxwings, Shrikes, Wrens, Mockingbirds, Catbirds, Thrashers, Robins, Thrushes, Veerys, Bluebirds, Gnatcatcher, Kinglets, Pipits
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 8, undated (Box 22, Folder 41)
        Vireos, Creepers, Warblers
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 9, undated (Box 22, Folder 42)
        (Passeriformes) Ovenbirds, Thrushes, Warblers, Redstarts, Larks, Blackbirds, Orioles,
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 10, undated (Box 22, Folder 43)
        Grackles, Cowbirds, Tanagers, Cardinals, Grosbeaks, Buntings, Finches,
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 11, undated (Box 22, Folder 44)
        Crossbills, Towhees, Sparrows
      - John Abbot Bird Illustrations Slide Catalog: Box 12, undated (Box 22, Folder 45)
        Misc., Covers and Titles Pages. Some slides of insects
      - Notes from Slide Boxes, undated (Box 22, Folder 46)
      - Box of Labels for Abbot Slides, undated (Box 22)
      - Box of Empty slide boxes, undated (Box 26)
        Contain Elsa Allen's hand-written notes and other contextual data.